Okay, so let's go through the forward pass
now.
So in the previous videos, we went through
steps number one and two.
So this now is my step number three,
where we are actually calculating the
forward pass, or we're doing a method
called the forward pass.
Now, in my step number three, then the
forward pass, we are calculating the early
start and the early finish for each
activity.
So for each of these
activities, we want to
calculate the early
start and the early finish.
Now, I'm also going to show you two
methods of doing this, right?
There's two ways of doing this.
And both methods are dependent on the
early start of the first activity,
right, the very first activity.
So in our case, early start of the first
activity, right, first activity is A.
So the early start of A could either be a
zero or a one.
These are the two methods.
Either it could be a zero or a one.
So sometimes they refer to as the zero
method and the one method.
So I'm going to go through the zero method
first.
Now, the basic difference between the zero
method and the one method, right?
So the early start, like I said, the early
start of A is either a zero or a one.
Now what zero means is that your
activities, all of your activities,
are going to finish sometime during the
day.
And so your next activity, subsequent
activities, will start exactly the same.
day.
Whereas the one method, right,
when A has an early start of one or the
first activity has an early
start of one, that means all of
your activities are going to
finish at the end of the day.
And so your next activity,
subsequent activity,
they're going to start the following day.
Right, they start the next day.
So that's the only difference between the
zero method and the one method.
So the zero method then with the first
activity is zero, right?
It starts at time zero.
That means all subsequent activities will
start the same day.
Whenever the activity finishes, all
subsequent activities start the same day.
With a one method, it means all subsequent
activities start the following day.
And then just with that difference, you'll
see what kind of complications we'll get.
So first we're going to go through the
zero method.
Then I've got, you
know, a few other videos,
why we're going to cover the one method.
Now, as I said, it's an all-or-nothing
rule.
Another way of also looking at the
difference in the zero and the one method.
With a zero method, think of a 24 hour
workday.
Machines are working 24-7.
As soon as he finish the work in one
machine, immediately you'll start the work
on the next machine, whereas a one method
will assume an eight-hour work day.
So you're scheduling
people, you're scheduling
them for eight hours to finish the work.
Whenever they finish the work,
the next activity will start the next day.
So that's another way of thinking of the
zero method and the one method.
Now, again, although
I'm talking about these in
days, there could be any
units of measure, right?
So if we're talking about weeks or months,
again, zero method means subsequent
activities start the same week or the same
month, the one method, subsequent
activities start the next week or the next
month.
So let's stick to days and let's talk
about the zero method.
So these are the basic steps involved.
So I just showed you
step number one here, the
early start of the first
activity times zero, right?
Now, we're calculating the early start and
the early finish, remember.
So in order to calculate the
early finish, then, early finish
of A is simply going to be
the early start plus a duration.
So for A, it's going to be 0 plus 2,
so A finishes on day 2.
Now, if A finishes on day 2, remember,
subsequent activities
will start the same day.
So B, D and G These are all dependent on A
As soon as A finishes B, D and G can start
And when do they start The same day As
soon as A finishes B, D and G start on day
2 So BD and G start on day 2 But let's
look at when they finish For B then,
when does B finish Starts on day 2 takes
four days 2 plus 4 finishes on day 6 Same
with D Starts on day 2 takes five days,
two plus five, finishes on day seven.
Same with G, starts on day two,
takes six days, finishes on day eight.
That's simple.
If you look at activity C, C is dependent
on B.
B finishes on day six, therefore C will
start immediately on day six.
It takes seven days, when does it finish,
day 13.
If you look at E, E again, is dependent on
D.
D finishes on day seven, when do we start
E?
same day, day seven.
It takes two days, when do we finish,
day none.
Now, let's look at F here.
F is dependent on both B and E.
So F is dependent on E and it's dependent
on B.
You can't start F until both B and E are
complete.
B finishes on day six, E finishes on day
nine.
So when is the absolute earliest we can
possibly start F, day nine?
We can't start F on day 6 because E won't
have completed.
We don't take the in-between date.
No, we have to start F when both B and E
are complete.
So whenever you have an activity,
a task or an activity that is dependent on
two or more prior activities, you always
take the highest number.
Always take the highest.
So in this case, F will start on day 9.
It takes six days, when does F finish?
9 plus 6, finishes on 50.
Same with H.
H is dependent on E and G.
G finishes on day 8.
E finishes on day 9.
Early so we can start H is the higher of
the 2, which is day 9.
And it takes 7 days, 9 plus 7,
when do we finish, day 16.
So now we have I.
I is dependent on C, F and H.
C finishes on day 13, F on day 15,
H on day 16, So when can, when the
earliest I can start, the higher of three,
which is day 16.
And it takes three days.
When does I finish?
16 plus three, day 19.
So there is our forward pass.
Now, the other thing I want to point out
here, what is this telling us?
It's telling us I, the last activity,
is finished on day 19.
So in other words, the entire project is
finishing on day 19.
And if you remember
from our step number one,
we calculated the critical path as day 19.
So the number that we calculated for the
critical path on the step number one
should be exactly the same as this number
here.
And step one, we
calculated our critical path
of day 19 and exactly the same thing here.
Our project is going to take 19 days.
And Ade, H and I are still on the critical
path.
All right, so that was the zero method
forward path.
us.